<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pursuit of peace. Briefly explained and plainly propounded in a sermon preached on the 29.th day of March, 1660. Unto a solemne assembly of the parishioners of the parish of Botolphs Algate London; on the composure of their late unhappie and too long continued differences. By Z.C. their unworthy pastor.</title>
            <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80849</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867666</idno>
  <idno type="VID">119987</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240955024</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6999</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1025_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208744</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867666</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99867666e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80849)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119987)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 152:E1025[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pursuit of peace. Briefly explained and plainly propounded in a sermon preached on the 29.th day of March, 1660. Unto a solemne assembly of the parishioners of the parish of Botolphs Algate London; on the composure of their late unhappie and too long continued differences. By Z.C. their unworthy pastor.</title>
                  <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 53, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T. Fawcet for James Nuthall, and are to be sold at his house in the Minories next doore to the Dolphin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Z.C. = Zachary Crofton.</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "May 10" and "May 31".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119987:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119987:1"/>
            <p>THE PURSUIT OF PEACE.</p>
            <p>BRIEFLY <hi>Explained and plainly Propounded</hi> IN A SERMON PREACHED on the 29.<seg rend="sup">th</seg> day of <hi>March,</hi> 1660, Unto a solemne Assembly of the Parishio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Parish of BOTOLPHS <hi>Algate</hi> LONDON; On the composure of their late unhappie and too long continued Differences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Z. C. <hi>their unworthy Pastor.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ROM. 12.18.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>If it be possible, as much as in you lyeth, live peaceably with all men.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>ZACH. 8.19.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Love Peace and Truth.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Tale est bonum Pacis; ut in rebus Creatis nihil graciosius soleat audir<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; nihil delectabilius concupisci, nihil utilius possideri. <bibl>August</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. Fawcet</hi> for <hi>James Nuthall,</hi> and are to be sold at his house in the <hi>Minories</hi> next doore to the <hi>Dolphin,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119987:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119987:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Hon:<seg rend="sup">ble</seg> THOMAS ALLEYN <hi>Lord Major,</hi> William Wylde <hi>Recorder,</hi> Francis Warner, <hi>and</hi> William Love, <hi>Sheriffes of the</hi> Honourable City of LONDON.</head>
            <head type="sub">Z. C. <hi>Wisheth the Blessing of the</hi> Peace-maker.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y</hi> LORD, <hi>and</hi> GENTLEMEN:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>To whom should <hi>A Tract of Peace</hi> bee presented for Protection, but to the <hi>Preservers of the Peace;</hi> in which respect (were there no other Cause for it) this <hi>Dedication</hi> cannot be judged a <hi>Solecisme,</hi> but this is not the only ground of this Presumption: No! these Lines (though not sounded in your eares yet) are laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your Eyes, as an humble and thankfull Testimony; that what in your publike Sessions of the Peace was by Mr. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder</hi> propounded, and perswaded; and by the paines and great trouble of you, <hi>my</hi> LORD, and Mr. <hi>Sheriffes,</hi> endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, hath been at length effected: Wherein though the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versness of my adversaries, prevented your intentions, and my desires, for your putting a period to our unhappie Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: yet I and my Friends must needs acknowledge, you were not the least instrumentall, in enforcing it; For my <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> the very countenance of men of Place is of great concernment in matters of Controversie: Some my <hi>Lord</hi> (who lately sate in your Lordships chaire) indulging falshood, violence, and vanity, did not a little abet, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimate the disturbers of my Peace; and so necessitate mee unto the defence of my own integrity, and interest by waies more answerable to the impudence of the opposition made against me, then my own naturall Genious: But your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi> and <hi>Worships</hi> no sooner gave in our Cause, the least pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="tcp:119987:3"/> testimony of your propensity unto justice, but the Scales were brought into an equipoise, that I might stand on even Ground to expostulate the insolencies and injuries of Men against men, God is my witnesse, and many good men know how earnestly I desired, and how eagerly I sought Peace with them whom I never wronged, and who never could in way of justice doe me more hurt then put me on a vexatious defence; yet whilest by arbitrary power, and extrajudiciall processe they could oppresse me, seemed to have Peace and would none of it, I beleeve (my Lord and Gentlemen) your observation of my willingnesse to procure peace, by pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all past wrongs, being but provided for as to future order, and secured from future violence and disturbance, as likewise of that Spirit of disorder and rudenesse, by which my Adversaries were acted, together with your favourable expression of your sence of the Iustice of my demands, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the submission made unto you had that influence on them as to incline them not only to seeke Peace, but to accept it on much harder termes, I was willing you should have made for them: So that the causes they constrained me to bring into your Courts came no more before you, save to be dismissed, so that our Peace (which occasioned these Instructions) is hereby returned to you from whom it sprang, having beene first propounded, and at after pursued by you, though concluded among our selves: Moreover this duty of pursuing Peace is so profitable to our Citty and Nation, and now so generally pretended to that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes worthy your Patronage, the which he doubts not to obtaine, who is —</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>My</hi> LORD <hi>and</hi> GENTLEMEN,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your humble and thank full Servant, in the Gospell of Peace.</hi> ZECH: CROFTON.</signed>
               <dateline>LONDON <hi>Algate.</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aprill</hi> 25.th, 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:119987:3"/>
            <head>Vnto the Inhabitants of the Parish of BOTOLPH'S without <hi>Algate</hi> LONDON, more especially the late Disturbers of our Peace now Reconciled.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends and Neighbours;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat amongst you J have Preached the Gospell with <hi>much Contention,</hi> in pursuit whereof, J have undergone <hi>good Report and bad report,</hi> been made a scorne to men, and reproach to neighbors, been persecuted with the height of Violence, outrage, and cruelty the worst of times could expresse, and the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of <hi>Englands</hi> shamefull, sinfull Revolutions, under most unjust, and usurping Tyrants could adminster is not only evident to such among you, as have been the <hi>Agents</hi> and <hi>Abetters</hi> thereof; or such as have been affected with my sufferings: but it hath been written in such legible Characters that all that run may read them, and the sound thereof hath been heard through our Land: J cannot but
<pb facs="tcp:119987:4"/> tell you, that I have and if you be but savingly convinced you will say it cause to rejoyce in my support, under, and escape out of all these many troubles: in this give me leave to play the foole, and boast; it is for the <hi>Gospels</hi> sake that I have suffered; J can appeale to the most of you, Whose Oxe or Asse have J taken? whom have J wronged? or defrauded? what cause did J give for all the calamity you created to me, your selves being witnesses, was it not the withstanding <hi>Error</hi> and Erronious incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant <hi>JOHN SIMPSON</hi> that enraged your spirits: till I denied the liberty of your Lusts, you never spied lewdness in my life, nor indeed endevoured to charge any; and that your whole contest hath been for <hi>Licentious liberty</hi> to heape up <hi>teachers</hi> to your itching eares; and intrude into my pulpit Impostors <hi>Jezabels which teach and seduce Gods people:</hi> your arbitrary orders, violent intrusions, and open out cryes <hi>he will not let</hi> Simpson (charged and convict of Preaching soul damning Doctrines) <hi>preach:</hi> doth plainly manifest: if the cause not calamity make a <hi>Martyr,</hi> J leave the truly sober and Religious to judge the matter of my joy and crowne of my Ministry: let me tell you freely I have reaped among you nothing but what I expected: I often said at my first comming I must not think to rake in a Waspes nest and not be stung; or fight with the Divell in his own dominions and not be wounded:
<pb facs="tcp:119987:4"/> It is matter of more admiration that J should stand in such opposition &amp; see the end of my conflict as a Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror then that I should be scratched in my credit, or woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in any my enjoyments; how many of my Brethren have concluded they must have sunke under my burden? whilst through grace J have borne up to the constant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of my Ministry, in both<note n="*" place="margin">Having published my tract of Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing: the vertue and value of Baptisme: prospering Prophan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse w<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>h other things since the heate of your Opposition.</note> Presse and Pulpit under all the conflicts assaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me armed with the advantages of wind and Sun: J must professe had I not enjoyed a good GOD, and cleare Conscience, and beene engaged in a Good cause the truth of the <hi>Gospell</hi> clouded, with many yeares liberty of Errour and erronious <hi>Teachers,</hi> who had made you a People of such opposition, not onely discoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, but deterring any Minister from comming among you, I had not endured to the end. J am a man subject to the same Infirmities with others; and have not been without my temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to throw downe my weapons, and leave the Field; had not Conscience (for you well know there is no outward enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to doe it) enforced to persist in the Contest: God hath now put a period to it; wee have seemed to rejoyce in the Peace concluded: may God have the Glory of it, in your future or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and subjection to the power of the <hi>Gospell.</hi> I have often professed to you, and protested in Prayer to GOD, <hi>Restraint</hi> of violence not <hi>Revenge</hi> was the end of those vexatious Courses you constrained me to use against you: and God hath given
<pb facs="tcp:119987:5"/> you into my hands that I might considering make it manifest; and how ever the little smart of some may make them fret, yet in coole blood J have not repaired my friend nor re-inbursed my selfe; though highly provoked by your foolish clamours, false accusations, unjust invasions, arbitrary and extrajudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all processe, mul iplyed Perjuries, violence oppressions, vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious groundlesse and malicious Persecution, nay by your rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous holding my friend by the throat, and Cruell exaction of the utmost mite the Law allowed you for (at the most) the rash re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke of those false Oathes of which I and others cannot but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verre, your Consciences know and (without your Repentance) the day of the Lord will make manifest you are Guilty, will make you clearly conclude, <hi>I only cut off the lap of your Garment,</hi> when your Head was in my hand: I pray give God the glory of his grace, and let men know the spight and envy you have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced in me; af<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er all the evill done me, I can abide your opposition, better then insult over your submission, I cannot but desire my kindnesses may melt you, least they heape up Coales of fire to consume you: Your Repentance towards God I am bonnd to pursue, and cannot but desire and waite for, that you may have peace with God, otherwise my Peace will but reprieve your pain; I beseech you consider your iniquity, and give glory to GOD, were it not that I should blazen your shame, I should have laid your sins in order before you; but you cannot but know that the confession of it to me, or before men will never establish a pardon without soule humiliation before God: Whilest I speake Peace to you, I cannot but be plaine with you, to put you in mind of your duty, for I may not heale your hurt flightly, whilest I really seeke the Salvation of your Soule; Being —</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull Pastor, seeking you not yours, ZECH: CROFTON.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>this 25.th of</hi> Aprill, <hi>1660.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119987:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE Pursuit of Peace. BRIEFLY</hi> Explained and soberly propounded in a Sermon Preached to a solemne assembly of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishioners of <hi>Botolph Algate, LONDON,</hi> on the <hi>29.<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
               </hi> of <hi>March, 1660.</hi> On the Composure of their late unhappie and too long continued differences.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Text in PSAL. 34.14.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seeke Peace and pursue it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Psalme doth by its owne In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription declare its Author and occasion, the <hi>Author</hi> was DAVID, who though most desirous of and inquisitive after Peace was all his dayes attended with warre, and sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with commotion and tumults; The <hi>occasion</hi> was when hee changed his <hi>tast</hi> (as the Hebrew) his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119987:6"/>
               <hi>Face or Countenance</hi> (as the Septuagint) his <hi>Gesture</hi> or <hi>behaviour</hi> (as our and other Translations read it) before ABIMELECH that was ACHIS<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King of <hi>Gath</hi> of the Philistines, before whom in feare of danger he counterfeited himself mad, scrabling on the doores of the Gate, and letting his Spittle fall on his beard, as is more fully to be read in the 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. Chap. This ACHISN is called ABIMELECH as being one <hi>Bino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis</hi> knowne by two names, as EBEN EZRA notes; or as his <hi>tytle of Honour</hi> as others; <hi>Father-King</hi> being like AVGVSTVS his <hi>Pater Patriae</hi> their stile of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; or rather because ABIMELECH was the common Name of the Philistine Kings, as the PHARAOHS of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> or CAESARS of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Psalme in the nature of it, is Gratulatory, or a solemne and thankfull acknowledgement of Gods mercy for delivering DAVID from that desperate danger; into which SAVLS cruelty had driven him, and it fals into three Parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A thankfull acknowledgment of Gods mercy in his escape, and the prevention of his feares, from <hi>verse</hi> 1. to <hi>vers.</hi> 11.</item>
               <item>2. A Doctrine of Piety, <hi>vers.</hi> 11. to <hi>vers.</hi> 19.</item>
               <item>3. A Doctrine of Faith in Gods mercy, to the end of the Psalme.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The text lyeth within the second part of the Psalm <hi>viz. The Doctrine of Piety:</hi> He that rightly praiseth GOD cannot but preach Piety to Men; the Psalmist therefore calleth on others in holiness to wait on God, of whose Power and Goodness hee had received Experience, and herein wee have —</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119987:6"/>1. A Preface inviting attention, <hi>Come yee Children hearken unto me, &amp;c.</hi> vers. 11, 12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Proposals of Pietie, and they are foure. 1. <hi>Keepe thy Tongue from evill, thy lips from speaking guile.</hi> 2. <hi>Depart from Evill.</hi> 3. <hi>Doe good.</hi> 4. <hi>Seeke Peace and pursue it,</hi> vers. 13.14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The perswasive Arguments or Motives to these duties, <hi>vers.</hi> 12.15, 16.</p>
            <p>The text we see then is the 4.<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Duty propounded, and that as conducing to life, many dayes and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Good <hi>to seeke Peace and pursue it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words themselves wee have to observe two Parts.</p>
            <p>An object propounded <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A double act to be performed towards that Object, <hi>Seeke Peace and pursue it.</hi> Wee shall explaine the termes in the explication of the Doctrine, which we thus propound unto your Consideration.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>Good men must seeke Peace and pursue it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the worke of all men, and that to which they are naturally enclined; who will not sound that Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho, <hi>Pacem te poscimus omnes,</hi> but It is after a more especiall manner charged on good men that professe unto the feare of God, that they seeke Peace and pursue it.</p>
            <p>In the consideration of this Doctrine I shall brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inquire into the severall kinds of Peace. 2. The generall nature of Peace. 3. The acts of seeking and pursuing Peace. 4. The arguments enforcing the Duty, and so make application of it: Of these in order, and first of the kinds of Peace.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119987:7"/>
            <p>The kinds of Peace are variously accounted, some reckoning them according to their quality, tell us of <hi>Pax temporis</hi> transient quiet among men, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is but for a time and ordinarily is very short; <hi>Pax pectoris</hi> the calmnesse of our owne Consciences which is also variable and often removed; <hi>Pax Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis</hi> an agreement with and enjoyment of GOD for ever.</p>
            <p>Others accounting of Peace by its properties, tells us of an <hi>inordinate Peace,</hi> when Subjects rule their Soveraignes, one of the foure things for which the earth is moved, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.22. <hi>Dissembling and hipocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Peace,</hi> like IVDAS kisse an harbinger of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; a <hi>wicked Peace,</hi> being a combination in sinne and confederacy of the wicked, like HEROD and PILATE; a <hi>just, honest and sincere Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But waving these I shall propound the kinds of Peace according to its subjects, and so it is fourefold.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Kind of of Peace.</note>First, <hi>Peace betwixt GOD and Man:</hi> and this is a Reconciliation whereby God is at one with man; his justice being satisfied, and his wrath appeased by the Merits and mediation of the Lord IESVS CHRIST, he is reconciled; his favour and goodwill is restored un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man; to him, his Compassion is extended; and that because CHRIST hath endured the <hi>Chastisement of our Peace:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 53.5.</note> This is the foundation of all other Peace purchased by the Lord IESVS <hi>the Prince of Peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn 2.2.</note> proclaimed in and by the Preaching of the Gospell <hi>the Glad-tidings of Peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.15.</note> by the Ministers the <hi>Embassadors of peace</hi> and accepted <hi>by Faith,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee have <hi>peace with GOD,</hi> so that we are no more pursued in his wrath nor punished for sinne, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119987:7"/> Gods <hi>friends,</hi> all his dispensations towards us being in mercy and faithfulness; and unto this must be added the <hi>Peace of contentation and holy submission to God:</hi> Whereby the enmity of our Flesh is remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and wee are resigned into the will and pleasure of GOD to doe or suffer his appointment, closing with the termes of Faith and Obedience by God propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or quietly without wrath or murmuration, endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Chastisements by him inflicted, such is the agreement betweene GOD and man, that God resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his favour to his Creature, and Man rejoyceth in his Creator: and is ruled by him and wholly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed up to him; acquiescing in <hi>the will</hi> of God in all cases and conditions, so that the tumults of the Soule are restrained, and all Waves of unquietnesse in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit are laid, and Calmnesse and Composure doth abide upon us in our attendances on GOD, untill wee are in Peace, and arrive at the rest appointed for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <p>The 2.<seg rend="sup">d</seg> kind of Peace is <hi>a Peace betweene Man and other Creatures:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Kind of peace.</note> Mans rebellion against GOD raised against him a resistance of all other Creatures which of Nature were made subject to him, but on the returne of divine favour they are reduced into due Subjection, and made to agree with man; <hi>they have a League with the stones of the field, and the beasts of <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he field are at peace with him,</hi> Iob. 5.23. for when GOD heholdeth a People to himselfe, he <hi>maketh a <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ovenant for them with the Beasts of the earth, with <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Fowles of heaven, and every thing that creepeth on t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Earth:</hi> Hos. 2.18. All things are reduced into the order, that they shall <hi>worke together for the good
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119987:8"/> of them that love GOD.</hi> Iam. 8.28.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Kind of peace.</note>The 3.<seg rend="sup">d</seg> kind of peace, is <hi>the Peace of a man with himselfe,</hi> and this is <hi>naturall</hi> in the subduing of our own passions, and stilling all those Noyses, Tumults, and stirres which anger, love, feare, desire, and the like are apt to provoke,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 13, Esth. 5, 14. Dan. 5.6.</note> like that of AMMON, who was sick of Love, or HAMAN tormented with anger and envie, or BELSHAZER who was disturbed by Dread and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and this is effected by the power of right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, regulating the affections, and restraining Passion according to the Counsell given to LVTHER, <hi>Vince a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s iram{que} tuam: a Christian and religious</hi> (when the Conscience is calmed and quieted) and all the Commotions thence arising doe cease and are still, and this is sometimes <hi>false, fained, and unsound,</hi> the Peace of Fooles and hopes of Hipocrites, which doe not and cannot continue, which doth spring from pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption, carnall Confidence, and security; is the Result of ignorance or impossibility of Gods holiness, Power, and Iealousie; and their imminent and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending danger against, which GOD expresseth his anger, and assureth that it must faile, <hi>Deu.</hi> 29.19. 1. <hi>Thes.</hi> 5.3. as it is a Peace <hi>sound and wel setled,</hi> flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the soule on the apprehension of our own in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tegrity, and assurance of divine favour unto the an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>swer of all our doubts, and abating of all feares an<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> passions, the soule being satisfied in God, and subord<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nate to his will; this is <hi>the Peace of the Gospell</hi> prayd for in behalfe of the Saints, and is <hi>the Peace which p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth all understanding,</hi> Phil 4.17. In which inded consisteth <hi>the Kingdome of GOD,</hi> Rom. 14.17. thiis Light in Darknesse, and establishment of the Spit
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119987:8"/> under all Commotions that doe compasse about the Righteous, <hi>Psal.</hi> 112.4, 5, 6, 7. wherein they continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally rejoyce.</p>
            <p>The fourth and last kinde of peace is <hi>betweene man and man:</hi> this is the Band of humane society;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Kind of Peace.</note> when men understand each other and agree together, and this is <hi>Peace publique,</hi> as it relates to multitudes, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, Countries, or Citties, and so is <hi>politicall</hi> in reference to the World, and <hi>Eclesiasticall</hi> in reference to the Church, and is excellently well described of St. AVSTIN, that it is <hi>ordinata imperandi et obediendi</hi> (and I would adde <hi>et alter utrum observandi) Concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> an orderly agreement to observe that order God hath appointment among men, as for Magistrates and Superiours to rule and command, Subjects and inferiours to serve, yeeld and obey; and Equals to give due respect each unto others.</p>
            <p>The inversion of humane order Engendreth all strife and Controversie in the world, the <hi>raigning of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant</hi> is one of the foure things by which the Earth is moved and cannot sustaine it selfe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.21, 22. Or this is a <hi>private personall Peace,</hi> when it is onely between man and man, individuall persons, and that either betweene good men, or good men with bad men; as ABRAHAM's peace with ABIMELECH, and IACOB's with ESAV, and it is in all <hi>politicall</hi> humane domestique affaires, the part of the Iust to have peace with the wicked, for as farre as it is possible wee must <hi>have peace with all men,</hi> Rom. 12.18.</p>
            <p>These are then the severall sorts and kinds of peace, and if you particulerly enquire which is the peace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in the Text and Doctrine, I might answer <hi>all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119987:9"/> of them,</hi> for without peace with GOD, there can bee no peace in our selves, nor betweene us and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men or Creatures; and in the enjoyment of that wee are infested to, and may expect all the rest: and in our text the Psalmist propounds his directions generally, as the fruit <hi>of the feare of God</hi> and the best way to <hi>long life ond seeking good,</hi> which cannot be without all these kindes of peace, therefore joyned with a <hi>shunning evill and doing good,</hi> and in this Latitude the Apostle PETER doth seeme to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, and explaine this Text, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10.11, 12. yet I shall wave the three first kinds of peace, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand specially the fourth, <hi>the Peace betweene man and man</hi> to be here propounded, as that which the Text doth manifestly point, and is most pertinent to our purpose and occasion, on which wee are now as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled: and so I passe to the second thing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe the generall nature of this Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peace</hi> according to the Latine <hi>pax</hi> is a <hi>Compact, Contract,</hi> or agreed union; which is so denominated <hi>a Paciscondo</hi> from Covenanting, because <hi>a pactis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis &amp; observandis deducitur,</hi> saith ZANCHY; Because peace is concluded and continued by making and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Covenants in which wee are conjoyned in one; in which it is answerable to the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is so called, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, derived from Levelling into one what before was divided and at distance, Peace is the coment of division and settlement of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straction, the nature of it is very accurately descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by St. AVSTIN, and it is —
<q>Concordantium in bono mentium ordinata tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitas.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119987:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An orderly serenity, a tranquility of minds agreeing in certaine good,</hi> to the better discerning of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Peace, according to this description I shall unfold it in these foure Conclusions or short propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions.</p>
            <p>First,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Peace.</note>
               <hi>an orderly serenity or tranquility is the forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Peace:</hi> Calmnesse and composure, silence and satisfaction of spirit is the forme of peace, it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layeth Stormes, asswageth tempests, restraineth lusts and violence; stills all Warres, tumults, and stirres, maketh husht and quiet all rage and rayling, dismisseth all fretting and fuming, dispelleth all Clouds of doubts and darknesse; the aire is cleared, and roaring waves are calmed <hi>by the Power of Peace;</hi> Warres doe cause Alarums, and noyses, stirres, and tumults which all are made to cease by the approach of Peace; in which respect (when God bringeth peace to a people) hee is said <hi>to cause all warres to cease,</hi> Psal. 46.9. and the Lord by <hi>a Peace and be still</hi> allayeth the tempest, and turneth the most tumbling Wave and tumultuous storme into a great calme <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.39. and so peace stands opposite to all <hi>strife and contention,</hi> distracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and disturbance, tumults and tumblings of the wicked, <hi>who never rest,</hi> Isa. 57.20. Peace is by the Latines called <hi>Otium,</hi> because it giveth <hi>a vacation from labour,</hi> danger and travaile, feare and trouble, an opportunity of silent attention and quiet agitation of our businesse and calling: it is called <hi>serenity</hi> as that which cleareth all troublesome aire, and maketh light and cheerfull, and it is <hi>a tranquility</hi> whereby the Sea-faring man is revived by the stilnesse of the wind, the calmnesse of the waves, and clearenesse of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119987:10"/> the Clouds encouraging his voyage, and assuring a safe arrivall at the desired haven; so that let peace be in what subject it will, <hi>tranquility, Calmnesse</hi> is the <hi>formality of it:</hi> when it is betweene <hi>God and man</hi> wrath is asswaged, and the expressions thereof cease, God appeareth not in the tempest or fire, but in the still and quiet winde: when it is in <hi>mans own spirit</hi> feare and anger are allayed, doubts and distractions are discharged, and all the tumblings of the passio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate soule ceaseth; that the winde becomes compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in <hi>the Common-wealth,</hi> Peace makes all ratling Drummes and sounding trumpets, and prancing Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses silent, and to stand still not to torment with any Alarums, the Smiths Anvile must not Hammer or be heard, in a quiet ISRAELL: in the <hi>Church</hi> all vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, Emulation, strife, quarrels, threates, chidings, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, disturbing contentions doe cease and are not heard.</p>
            <p>But whilst you observe calmnesse and tranquility to be the formality of peace, wee must not forget its adjunct <hi>an orderly tranquility</hi> for every quietnesse, si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and stilnesse is not peace; tranquility doth not properly exist, but <hi>by Order;</hi> if confusion be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by power and violence, it may meet with no present resistance and yet enjoy no peace; when <hi>Servants raigne</hi> and civill order is by tyranny, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surpation inverted; and other mens Rights invaded by force and Armes, and quietnesse occasioned by the present conquest, yet Commotions and disturbances are at hand so that watch and ward with all warlike Posture must maintaine it: If AHAB have one quiet turne in NABOTH's Vineyard, the next will meet him
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119987:10"/> with an harsh Alarum of, <hi>hast thou kild and taken pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session?</hi> and ATHALIAH may abide a few yeares in a quiet possession of her usurped kingdome, but you shall shortly heare her peace disturbed with an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry of <hi>Treason, Treason,</hi> nature cannot secure the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version of order; the <hi>Earth cannot sustaine it selfe under a raigning Servant,</hi> the roaring raging waves may be a while stilled by some banke, but yet it boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and swells in it selfe untill at length it overflow the Banke: and power and strength may bridle and restraine the rage of men, but can never secure Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion; nor settle disorder in Peace: Usurpers and unjust men goe not without their subjects Grudgings, grumblings and discontents; nor yet without their own feares, and Iealousies; and therefore sleepe not without the constant Alarums of Warre: <hi>Tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> doth not more formally constitute <hi>Peace</hi> then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der doth constitute Tranquility; when humane pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er runs in a channell of Righteousness it runs smooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and quietly, but violence, injustice, rebellion, and disorder doth make it rage and roare: but wee passe to the second conclusion, and that is, —</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The mind is the prime and proper subject of Peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Peace.</note> the mind is the <hi>seat of the Passions,</hi> according to its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions <hi>they are acted, and allayed;</hi> and so the prime and proper subject of all strife, debate, contention, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietnesse and disturbance; <hi>fightings without</hi> meeting <hi>with feares within</hi> did disturbe the Apostles peace at MACEDONIA 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.5. and the Apostle JAMES doth well and clearely resolve <hi>from whence comes Wars and fightings,</hi> even <hi>from within us</hi> the innate corruption of minde, and inbred lust, the inordinate of affection, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119987:11"/> irregularity of passion doe engender all inward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions and all outward confusions a pleasant coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and calme condition the world is of little va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue under the perturbation of mind, <hi>for in Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the heart is sorrowfull,</hi> Prov. 4.13. nor indeed can it be ordinarily enjoyed, for it is the <hi>merry heart that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a cheerefull countenance,</hi> Prov. 15.13. an anxious soule and afflicted mind is so torne with care, and tos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with passion, tormented with doubts, feares, Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies, and other perturbatious, that all the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the world cannot settle or secure its peace; what shall wee tell you of CAINES <hi>convinced mind,</hi> or AMMONS <hi>Love-sicke humour,</hi> or IOB's <hi>wounded spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> or the <hi>heathens furies,</hi> following a man from place to place through all changes &amp; conditions, which kept them under those Alarums, inward conflicts wracking debates, tumbling &amp; tumultuous thoughts, and affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting apprehensions; that although they are able to reckon up their high honours, ample possessions, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant favoures, and all the good the world can afford, yet are not appeased or quieted: but conclude <hi>all this doth not availe mee,</hi> though there appeare against him no enemy, yet the sound of Warre is alwayes in his eares; nor can the attendance of his friends, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of all councels, comforts, and perswasions naturall or religious assure his peace: <hi>all musicke to his heavy heart is but like the taking away of a garment in cold weather, and as vinegar to Nitre,</hi> an Alarum to his soule, and aggravation of his sorrow, so that the mind must be the subject of Peace by our selves pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed.</p>
            <p>Nor can wee be at peace with men <hi>unlesse the mind
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119987:11"/> bee the subject of it;</hi> for <hi>a raging heart</hi> goeth not without <hi>a revenging hand;</hi> however it bee restrained by want of oportunity: wee deny not but there may a Friendly deportment, amiable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, faire speech, and friendly correspondence which are the comments on, and tokens of Peace, so as that a man may with AGAG appeare with confidence and say, <hi>Surely the bitternesse of Death is past,</hi> though it be to his very execution; wicked men doe ordinarily speake Peace unto their neighbour, <hi>when mischiefe is in their heart,</hi> as <hi>Psal.</hi> 28.3. The words of their mouth <hi>may be smoother then Butter but Warre is in the heart,</hi> Psal. 55.21. AMMON may bee entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned like a Brother at ABSALONS table; and yet in the midst of his mirth meet with the instruments of Warre and influence of an hatefull mind, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.22. and <hi>art thou in health my Brother?</hi> may be the faire Preludium of IOABS rage against his Brother A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MASA, who is presently slaine; like IVDAS-kisse the very act of Treason delivering up his Master: and ANDRONICVS (the Greeke usurping Tyrant) with compassionate sighs and teares, cruelly murthering all his Nobles: nothing is more unsafe then the faire lookes of a festred heart, so that peace enjoyed, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed in our selves; or towards others <hi>must be seated in the mind,</hi> for if our passions be not mastered by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and Religion, there can be no peace; the mind composed by confidence in God, estates a man <hi>in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Peace,</hi> Psal. 112. malice not mastered by true charity and a reconciled mind doth onely lurke for an opportunity of Warre and mischiefe: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apostle doth well pray that <hi>the Peace which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119987:12"/> passeth understanding may preserve our heart and mind,</hi> Phil. 4.7. &amp; doth direct the Christian studying peace to make the peace of God <hi>Ruler Moderator</hi> in his heart, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.7. for our Lusts affections and passions restrained and regulated, peace may be enjoyed, wrath appeased, strife and Debates will cease: and thus much for the 2.<seg rend="sup">d</seg> Conclusion, I now passe to the Third.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Peace.</note>
               <hi>Agreement is the ground of Peace:</hi> The minds consent commands quietnesse: and composeth all noyse and stirres, whilest differing mindes cannot but occasion divided affections and actions: God expos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulating with ISRAELL doth urge the necessity of their consent to God with a <hi>can two walke together unlesse they be agreed?</hi> Amos, 3.3. different appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions must needs produce difference in words and actions; Confusion of tongues (the minds exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor) opened the doore to all commotion, till the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults in building BABELL, warre was a stranger upon the Earth: <hi>pacis Concordia nutrix,</hi> Consent is the nurse of peace, if men agree in one it is not broken, and when divided spirits understand one another, Peace is thereby restored: this agreement is no other save that humane verity, publique faith, and Orators eloquence that reason discoursed to mutuall conviction and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocall consent, or agreement, of which the heathen Orator thus speaketh, <hi>Societatis humanae vinculum est Ratio et oratio, qua docendo, discendo, communicando, disceptando, judicando conciliant inter se homines,</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and discourse is the bond of humane society, whereby men by instruction, expostulation, discourse and debate are brought to agree each with other; mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes of mind doe alwayes cause mutinies, murmura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119987:12"/> Iarres and strife, and must be rectified before peace can be returned: how deadly was the fewde, and dangerous the warre conceived and concluded on by the ten tribes against <hi>Reuben, Gad, and the halfe tribe of Manasseh,</hi> on a mistake of their work and meer mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apprehension of their <hi>Altar-building?</hi> but how soone stilled, appeased, and diverted, when by prudent serious expostulation the misconception was corrected, and all minds agreeing in the quality of the act did not only recede from present strife; but rejoyce each in other as they indeed were brethren? God &amp; nature hath taught men to break off the war by treaties, expostulations, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, rationall discourses, &amp; convictions of the equity and justice of things that fall in strife; Gods counsell and command was to court before they did constraine a consent from an enemy; <hi>When thou cōmest nigh to a City to fight against it proclaime peace, and if it make answer of peace, then thou shalt not destroy it:</hi> Deut. 20.10.11. rayling RABSHAKEH that he might worke the people to a ready consent to his demands will speake in the <hi>Iewes</hi> language, that he may be understood by them, as well as by their Princes, <hi>Isa.</hi> 36. Consent and agreement is that <hi>Domina rerum, pacis comes, otii{que} socia, et Reipublicae quaedam qu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>si alumna et nutrix;</hi> as <hi>Cicero</hi> saith, that regulatrix of affaires, companion of Peace, and preserver of the Republique, without which it cannot subsist; Agreem<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt is the only end of mediation to the appeasing of wrath and anticipation of strife and warre, by rectifying of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and b<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>getting a right understanding betweene divided parties: Discord disposeth to destruction, and Division to desolation; <hi>Divide &amp; Impera,</hi> is the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119987:13"/> Machivilian maxime, and a <hi>Kingdome divided against it selfe cannot stand</hi> is our Christian Aphorisme, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.25. Discord in the Reformed Church is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly designe of the Iesuite because the disturbance of Peace and order; for <hi>where there is strife there is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion and evill workings,</hi> saith the Apostle <hi>Iames</hi> 3.16. Different opinions cannot but divide the affections; whatever the pretended moderation of our Times shall suppose to the contrary; <hi>Ʋnity is the only argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of amity,</hi> and so improved by the Apostle, who adviseth to be of <hi>one mind and live in Peace,</hi> 2 Cor. 13.11. and the <hi>keeping of the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace;</hi> for that unity is the line that runnes through our Religion, <hi>One body, one spirit, one hope, one God, one faith, one Baptisme,</hi> Ephes. 4.3, 4, 5. If peace bee preserved in the Common-wealth it must be as St. AVSTIN saith, <hi>Ordinata concordia</hi> an orderly agreement to Relative duties: In the Church a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to the same common principles, such as in any capacity cannot live each with other without jarres, strife and debare, are like the Pitchers in the Fable swimming downe the streame and can sound no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther noise save — <hi>Si collidimur frangimur, If wee clash wee cleave:</hi> So that I may well conclude this third Conclusion with that of the Poet, concerning Concord effected by Discourse, and established in the Right apprehension of and assent unto each other.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ante Jovem generata, decus divunique hominum{que}</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>qua sine non tellus pacem, non aequora norunt;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iustitiae consors, tacitum{que} in pectore Numen.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:119987:13"/>
               <l>Concord is Eternall, GOD's and Mans renowne,</l>
               <l>by which to Sea, Earth Heaven peace is knowne.</l>
               <l>Faiths consort, in mans brest a deity most still,</l>
               <l>the mind 't appeaseth and Commands the will.</l>
            </q>
            <p>When disagreeing natures are reconciled, that <hi>the Lambe and the Wolfe may lie downe together,</hi> and Saints are all of <hi>one mind and one mouth</hi> in the Lord, spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the same things, and thinking the same things; then add not till then shall perfect Peace be possessed.</p>
            <p>The 4.<seg rend="sup">th.</seg> and last is, <hi>That good must be the subject matter of agreement, unto the obtainment of Peace:</hi> Calmness of mind is the <hi>forme</hi> and consent is the <hi>Ground,</hi> yet if Good be not the <hi>matter about which we consent,</hi> and from whence Peace doth flow we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enjoy it; nor indeed is it properly to be called Peace; <hi>Evill</hi> in its nature is and must be the object of Hatred, enmity and opposition; <hi>Hatred of every false way,</hi> is the worke of DAVID in the very way of Peace; the God of peace doth engage us into an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and absolute warre against sinne, engaging to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist striving against sinne unto blood,</hi> Heb. 12.4. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to the actings of prophanesse is <hi>Conspiracie</hi> not Peace, <hi>Confederacie</hi> not Union, like unto that of the Enemies of the Church in <hi>Psal.</hi> 83.5. <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.13, 14. against which wee are expresly warned in <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.10. <hi>My sonne if sinners entice thee consent thou not,</hi> and in <hi>Isa.</hi> 8.12. <hi>Say not a Confederacy with them who say a Confederacie:</hi> The wicked doe live in an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment each with other notion any principles of Good, but in an opposition to the Godly, and in order to their destruction; they would not, they could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119987:14"/> amongst themselves, were it not in this one thing <hi>opposition of Good,</hi> they would wage warre one against another, had they not Gods people against whom they bend their bow, and combine their strength; so that there is a combination of power, no concord in principles, <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> can strike hands to crucifie Christ, like dogs they would worrie one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, yet conjoyne to pursue the Hare when started, and whatever peace they seeme to enjoy in themselves It is <hi>but an agreement with death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 28 15.</note>
               <hi>and a covenant with hell</hi> whom they are resolved to embrace; which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not consent to their impunity: but they have no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord with God, nor give any consent to his wayes; and th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>refore <hi>there is no Peace to the wicked,</hi> saith my GOD, <hi>Isa.</hi> 57.20, 21. The <hi>Scripture doth make truth and peace,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 20.19. <hi>Eschewing evill do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good and pursuit of Peace,</hi> 1. Pet. 3.11. <hi>Peace and holinesse,</hi> Heb. 12.14. Constant comcomitants, and inseparable associats, as the cause and effect, for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and obedience, Holinesse and truth, can only se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure our Peace; If <hi>men goe out of the way, doe not good, their throat become an open Sepulcher, with their tongues they use deceipt, their mouth be full of cursing and bitternesse, their feet are swift to shed bloud</hi> and the like, it must needs be concluded that <hi>the way of peace they have not knowne, the feare of God is not before their eyes,</hi> Rom. 3.12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. the God of peace makes it a quarrel against his Prophets, that they <hi>heale the hurt of the Daughter of his people slightly, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing peace, peace when there is no peace,</hi> Iere. 8.11. the founds of Peace in the mouths of 400 false Prophets are but the summons of AHAB to War, and death at RAMOTH GILLEAD, in 1 King. 22.22; and the same
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119987:14"/> God of peace contendeth against his people for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting with the wicked in sin, when thou <hi>seest a theefe thou consentedst with him, and art a companion for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers:</hi> Psal. 50. v. 18.19: nay for their very lax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity and lukewarmnesse against errror and evill, it is his complaint, <hi>they are not valiant for the truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 9.3.</note> it cost old ELY deare that hee did expresse no more enmity against sin, though wee reade not that he did strike hands with, or consent unto it: 1. SAM. 3. the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Peace doth not only debarre from <hi>having fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship with the unfruitfull workes of darknesse,</hi> bu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doth also direct us <hi>to reprove them,</hi> Ephes. 5 8. and engage us earnestly <hi>to contend for the faith delivered to the Saints,</hi> Iude, 3. Correction for disorder and chastisements of iniquity is so farre from the <hi>breach,</hi> that it is the <hi>preservative</hi> of Peace; the sword is no lesse civill then military, as much an ornament to the Magistrate as the ma<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of War: the Rod becoms the hand of a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Father no lesse then of a tyrant or a Master; leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; indulgence of sin will afford but a wofull peace: It is therefore much more madnesse to conclude all men enemies to peace who only waite on, and walke with God in duetie, and cannot, will not consent to evill, and confederate in wickednesse: DAVID and IEREMIAH <hi>(though against every man and every man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them)</hi> were men of Peace: what ever contests lie in the way <hi>marke the perfect man, and behold the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right? the end of that man is Peace,</hi> Psal. 37.37. for he agreeth with and consumeth to all certaine good propounded by God or man.</p>
            <p>Thus then I have explained to you the generall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Peace according to this description, which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119987:15"/> may be a touchstone to our quietnesse, where wee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy true peace <hi>which the world cannot give</hi> the Grace, priviledge of peace, <hi>peculiar to the children of Peace,</hi> there will be <hi>Calmnesse and Composure,</hi> no boyling pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, fretting fumes, rayling language, ratling drums, roaring Cannons, or raging spirits, but all is still se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and quiet without disturbance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The minde is mastered</hi> by reason and Religion, and mastereth all the powers of soule and body, <hi>the heart is ruled</hi> and ruleth both tongue and hand.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Agreement,</hi> consent and concord in one, and the same end and meanes, desire and demand, taketh away all cause of strife wrath and contests, and so the fire goeth out.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For that good is apprehended, and embraced e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill shunned and avoided: I now therefore passe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the 2.<seg rend="sup">d</seg> thing, and that is to shew what it is to seeke this peace and pursue it, wee have discovered the prize, and must now enquire how to possesse it, wee have found the prey, the cunning is in catching it that it may not escape us and first:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What it is to seeke Peace.</note>
               <hi>Wee must seeke Peace:</hi> It is a pearle and not found common among p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bbles of price and value, and not to obtained without diligence and difficulty, wee <hi>must seeke it</hi> and that sometimes <hi>sorrowing:</hi> The terme which is here rendred <hi>Seeke</hi> is very Emphaticall and significant; It is <hi>Bakesh</hi> of <hi>Bakash quaerere</hi> to seeke, but it imports Enquiry with earnestness and industry, as the man of <hi>understanding seeketh knowledge,</hi> Pro. 15.14. Which as MERCER saith, is <hi>mag<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s conatu et studio quam interrogatione et verbis,</hi> is by words, out-cries, enquiries, and earnest expostulations; but chiefly by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119987:15"/> labour and industry of mind and body, the Apostle PETER retaining the Septuagint, rendreth this Hebrew phrase, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by a Greeke word no lesse sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant then the Hebrew; but something more it sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth <hi>a seeking with affection,</hi> and the utmost desire of discovery, as HEROD sought the Lord IESVS to kill him, who sought him by a slaughter of the babes of BETHLEEM not sparing his own Child;<note place="margin">Math 2.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> concluding in so generall a search he could not escape his hands: and thus sometimes <hi>Pax bello quoeritur,</hi> the sword maketh search for peace: <hi>a seeking with acuracie</hi> and strictnesse of observation of all occurrences that may administer an opportunity to obtaine peace as the Devill going about like a roaring Lyon <hi>seeking whom he may devoure,</hi> 1. PET. 5.8.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>a seeking with ardency and esteeme</hi> by way of care, as giving preheminence unto the object above other things, as the Lord did <hi>seeke his Fathers glory,</hi> in IOHN 7.18 8.50: In short it is to <hi>seeke with curiosity and resolution,</hi> as the earnest dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putant seekes out a question in the Schooles; or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting Tyrant doth enquire and extort a discovery by racking torment, in all which sences the word is used in Scripture, and doth well set out mens dutie in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence unto peace, and that is thus.</p>
            <p>Whilest Peace is <hi>not obvious to every eye,</hi> it is a Pearle of prize not found in the surface of the Earth, but obscured in the bowels and heart, so that of many men it must needs be acknowledged <hi>the way of Peace they have not knowne,</hi> Rom. 3.17. And whilest Peace is not <hi>obtained without diligence and difficulty,</hi> BALA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AM<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> short winded wish will never make him <hi>dye the death of the righteous:</hi> wee must therefore: 1. <hi>Sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119987:16"/> affect our hearts with the worth and excellency of peace:</hi> dignity being the great enducement to duty under difficulty, worth causing warinesse to gaine and keepe: 2. <hi>Sincerely desire it</hi> as the one thing we want, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which wee must not rest or be content, know that Commotion can afford no comfort: 3.<seg rend="sup">ly</seg>, <hi>Seriously enquire after peace;</hi> cast about our thoughts, crave Counsell and advise, hearken to Instruction and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe; Read every Riddle; and unty all knots, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve all questions that may informe our minds and direct our feet into the way of Peace: 4.<seg rend="sup">thly</seg>
               <hi>Studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 11.29.</note> and with all our strength <hi>to apply</hi> our whole man to all actions in the improvement of all opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which tend unto peace: Taking upon us CHRISTS yoake: doing all duties against all difficulties under the greatest discouragements that can be, in short, it is to <hi>stand in the waies to see and aske for the old Paths and to walke therein,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 6.29.</note>
               <hi>that wee may at length find rest unto our soules,</hi> and thus then wee are to seeke Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What it is to pursue peace.</note>Secondly, Peace is not more <hi>darke</hi> to discover then <hi>difficult</hi> to obtaine, it is not more <hi>obscure</hi> to meet then <hi>hard to be overtaken</hi> when sought out and seene; Mans sinne hath provoked GOD to take Peace a way from him, that he wanders in commotion, unlesse the Lord directs his feet into the way of Peace; nay Peace is by na<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure farre off from any one of us; wrath and envie, strife and contention, discord and division, is as naturall to us as our very beings; and hereby peace is driven from us, and flyeth away; So that if ever wee will enjoy it, we must <hi>up and after it;</hi> not be sati<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fied that we seeke and make a discovery of it,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119987:16"/> but also <hi>pursue</hi> and follow after till wee fasten on it and possesse it.</p>
            <p>The terme here rendred <hi>pursue</hi> is from the Hebrew word <hi>Radaph,</hi> no lesse Emphaticall and significant then the former, it signifieth a <hi>following with all force</hi> and <hi>fervency,</hi> as the <hi>Hound or hunter</hi> doth follow his prey, leaping hedge and ditch; encountring dangers and difficulties, induring hurts and hazards to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take it: or as the resolved <hi>Courser</hi> in running of his Race, regardeth no Remoraes, nor will be retarded by any thing that lyeth in his way, but flings it out of his way with violence, and flies with all force unto the appointed Gaole, that hee may gaine the prize: or as the <hi>furious Horse</hi> that followeth the victory with all vigour, fretting and foaming for very rage of desire; not stopped by Darts or arrowes, nor startled by the ratlings of Drums and Trumpets; but rusheth into the battell and returneth not without the victory: It is a word when referred to the <hi>wicked Pursuit of sin,</hi> signifieth such eagernesse and industry that death it selfe doth not divert them and is therefore well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed by SOLOMON, Prov. 11.19. <hi>he pursueth evill to his own death:</hi> so that the Pursuit of Peace is with a ravenous Appetite; a restlesse mind and resolved spirit to fly farre and fast, to run too and fro with force and fervency, in every action, and use of all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed meanes to follow Peace; and not to be diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or stayed, by all the danger and difficulty may lie in our way: The Apostle PETER following the Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuagint hath rendred this word (as the former) by a word in the Greeke no lesse emphaticall: 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from the originall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119987:17"/> signifieth <hi>a Pursuit in Battell, a persecution of an enemy,</hi> It is ordinarily used to expresse the earnest desires, and utmost diligence, Attempts, and endeavours that the most necessary enjoyments, or most excellent endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments can engage: and so it is ordinarily taken in a good sence, as in 1. Thes. 5.15. <hi>Follow good?</hi> 2. TIM. 2.11. <hi>Follow after Righteousnesse,</hi> 1. Cor. 14.1. <hi>Follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Charity?</hi> Phil. 3.12, <hi>J follow after, that</hi> I may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend on which one noteth the Apostle would not simply follow;<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Airdy.</hi>
               </note> but follow as a Persecutor, who would not rest in himselfe, nor be stayed by other things, and in Heb. 12.14, <hi>Follow Peace and Holinesse?</hi> so that what ever is incumbent on man in order to good, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse, and Charity; to the marke of the price of his high calling and holinesse, <hi>without which no man can see God, the same</hi> is to be done in the Pursuit of Peace: The Greeke word doth usually expresse the Pursuit of the persecutors of the Church with fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and fury, with insatiable appetites, and impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Spirits; who leave no councell unconsulted, nor meanes unattempted, loose no opportunity, stop not at any difficulty, but with rage run on to their Ruine, to accomplish their wicked designe in which alone they insult and are satisfied.</p>
            <p>The Word thus explained doth plainly teach us, that to pursue Peace is <hi>earnestly to desire it</hi> with a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous appetite and fervent affection; which are the wings of the Soule, by which wee fly and follow it: so that our Spirit is restlesse, unquiet, and unsati<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fied untill wee be at Peace; wee savour no food without the Salt of Peace; wee are ready to give any thing in exchange for Peace, accounting <hi>a dry Morsell with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119987:17"/> quietnesse better then a House full of Sacrifices with strife,</hi> Prov. 17.1: a <hi>dinner of herbs with Love better then a stalled Oxe and hatred,</hi> Prov. 15.17. Secondly To have <hi>established Resolution of mind</hi> to assault all difficulties and dangers, and indure all hurts and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards that may lie in our way to peace: Purpose must pricke forward our own backward Spirits, and provoke us to put out strength to obtain it. 3.<seg rend="sup">dly</seg>
               <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly to apply our selves to the obtainement of it,</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring by all meanes to be at Peace, bridling our Passions, restraining wrath, remooving envy, refusing strife and contention: Forbearing wrong and violence, carefull to live void of offence towards God and man; shutting our eares against Tale-bearers, and our soules against Iealousies, surmises, and false suspicions; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready to forgive; patient and long suffering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards offenders, offering Peace to them who offend us, and forgiving freely such as say they have offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; acknowledging the offences wee have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, being in all things meeke, gentle, and easie to be intreated; and ready to recede in some things from our own just priviledges to propagate Peace: so that no opportunity of accommodation shall offer it selfe, but wee will imbrace it to pursue Peace, no meanes can cast an aspect towards peace, but wee will make an essay and endeavour it: wee will according to the Apostles counsell <hi>follow the things of Peace,</hi> Rom. 12.18.14.19. <hi>If it be possible as much as in us lyeth,</hi> by faire, just, and honest cariage, plaine, sober, rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall discourse, Conviction and expostulation; free cheerfull and speedy condescension; Wee will have peace with all men, and this is verily and indeed to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119987:18"/> seeke Peace and pursue it.</p>
            <p>You have had the Doctrine explained, and doe I hope understand the nature of Peace, and the duty you ow unto it <hi>(viz)</hi> to seeke peace and pursue it: our next worke is to let you see why <hi>good men must with care seeke Peace and pursue it,</hi> and the Reasons I might render for this Duty and Doctrine might bee many; but I shall resolve them into two generall grounds <hi>viz:</hi> The unparalleld <hi>Excellency,</hi> and the unspeakeable <hi>necessity</hi> of Peace, and first of the first.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reason. </seg>1</label> Peace must be sought and pursued, because it is of <hi>unparalleld excellency, and of matchlesse price and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue:</hi> Dignity is the cause of dread and Spurre of dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, men will worke, toile, travell, compasse Sea and Land, and contest with all danger, and difficulty to obtaine matters of moment, and things of value: men digge deepe, and run in danger in the bowels of the Earth; that they may seeke for, find, and fetch out Gold, the chiefest Mettall: and peace is beyond the purchase of Gold, such is the transcendent excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of peace, that both prophane and sacred story sceme<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be at a losse to extoll it to its due point of worth:<note place="margin">Livie.</note> the Heathen concludes <hi>Pax omnium rerum pulcherrima et optima,</hi> it is the fairest flower in natures Garden, and the best of all possessions in the World, and that is more then <hi>Pax bello Potior,</hi> to be preferred before warre, and this is but a little short of St. AVS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TINE account of the worth of Peace, when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes <hi>Pax est maximum homini bonum,</hi> mans chiefest good: Peace is so excellent in it selfe, that the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then<note place="margin">Dulce est no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men pacis res eam jucunda &amp; salutaris qua non modo ij quibus s<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>usum natura sedit se<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> etiam tecta at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que agri laetari videntur. <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </note> Orator tells us not only such as hath sense and discretion doe desire it, but the very fields and houses
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119987:18"/> rejoyce in it: Peace is the preserver of our persons and priviledges, the maintainer of order and honour, the mother of all increase and plenty; and indulger of all pleasure and the delights of Nature,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Pyrrho.</note> by Peace wee have wives, kinsfolke and children; feasts, friends and fruitfull Vines; Health and all happiness as saith the Greeke Poet: And in that respect it may well be called <hi>Optima rerum,</hi> &amp; concluded the <hi>most excellent of enjoyment:</hi> men who live by sense and not by faith may well be dazled with its dignity, so farre as to imbrace peace on any Termes, preferring <hi>the most unjust Peace before the most just Warre,</hi> as that which is desired and imbraced by the most valiant Warriour devoted to martiall Atchievements, as the height of his honour, and utmost of his ambition; As that which he finds not purchaseable by the excellencies of Nature or all the Riches in the World, in respect of which the Poet sings of the warlike Medes, and furious Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians that they seeke peace, —
<q>
                  <l>Otium bello furiosa Thrace,</l>
                  <l>Otium Medi Pharetra decori,</l>
                  <l>Grosph, enon gemmis nec purpurave,</l>
                  <l>vale, nec auro:<note place="margin">Horace.</note>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Nor doth Peace shine with more splendor in the Church of God; for all the excellencies under Law or Gospell are prised under this terme <hi>Peace;</hi> the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew alone doth signifie the perfection of all kind of Blessings both for soule or body; and therefore was the ordinary expression of affection, and common sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutation <hi>Shalom</hi> used among them, as in <hi>Gen.</hi> 43.27.<note place="margin">2 Kings 4.26. <hi>Buxtof. Mercer. Leigh.</hi>
               </note> The Criticks in this tongue tell us, that it imparts all health and perfect prosperity in Person, Name or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119987:19"/> and the Greekes usually understand the wish of Peace to comprehend the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Grace, setled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, composure, and all endowments of mind, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> health and strength of body, with all things conducing unto long life, and Natures glory; and the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Wealth and worship, Riches and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, increasing treasure and flourishing estate: In respect of the extent and excellency of Peace, this sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutation is not only restrained by our Saviour; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so directed to his Apostles, <hi>in whatsoever House or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yee enter, say, Peace be in this place,</hi> Math. 10.13; Peace is the Emphasis of all Gospell excellency, God is set forth by the Epithite of <hi>the God of Peace,</hi> Heb. 13.20, 2. Thes. 3.16. and Iesus Christ the <hi>Prince of Peace,</hi> Isa. 6.9. The excellency of Christ sufferings is in this they were the <hi>Chastisements of our Peace;</hi> Isa. 53.5, and the Covenant of Grace is a <hi>Covenant of Peace:</hi> The word is a <hi>Gospell of Peace,</hi> Ephe. 6.15. the Ministers honour is that they are <hi>Ambassadors of peace:</hi> And the beauty of their feet is that they do bring the <hi>Glad tidings of Peace,</hi> Rom. 10.5: Nay, in briefe the very excellency of the Estate of Grace and Glory (which is indeed the <hi>summum bonum</hi>) is that it is an <hi>Estate of peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 26, 3.57.2. 1 Pet. 1.3, Gal. 6, 16.</note> and accordingly to be <hi>sought for and pursued:</hi> For let us imagine with our selves what excellency soever; And it is implyed in, and expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, nay, enjoyed by Peace, and this is a sufficient in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement to every ingenious Spirit, (wound to any competent height of Nobility, to follow after things as they are excellent) that they seeke peace and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reason. </seg>2</label> Secondly, Peace and the pursuit of it is not only e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119987:19"/> excellent; but also <hi>indispensably necessary:</hi> There may be some among you, who must <hi>seeke for Want,</hi> and will pursue peace no longer then they are driven; So contentions is their disposition, and low their Spirit, that if they be not constrained they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, will not condescend to the least proposall for peace; If such want ingenuity to moove themselves to seeke peace, as it is excellent, let them know this Reason is suited to them, to affect them with the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of peace; that Want may <hi>drive,</hi> whilest Worth cannot <hi>draw</hi> them to seeke and pursue it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peace</hi> I say, is <hi>indispensably necessary,</hi> and also the <hi>Pursuit of it:</hi> Not only the <hi>Object,</hi> but also the <hi>Act</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versant about it, the priviledge must be possessed, and prescription relating to it observed; peace is a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit necessary to be enjoyed; and the seeking of peace and pursuing of it, is a Duty no lesse necessary to bee performed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peace is a mercy Benefit necessary to bee enjoyed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Peace neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary.</note> It is not a thing of indifferency and meere accident,, or Conveniency to mans condition; but of the very es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence thereof, if there must be the enjoyment of any, the least measure of Comfort or content in it: can any Christian man seriously observe <hi>the pressing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasions of Scripture</hi> to follow the things which make for Peace, <hi>Rom</hi> 14.19, as farre as may be if it be pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible live peaceably with all men, <hi>Rom,</hi> 12.18. live in peace, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11; Be at peace among your selves 1. <hi>Thes.</hi> 5.13, and follow Peace and holinesse; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which no man can see God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, The <hi>Patheticall Wishes and Prayers of the best men for peace:</hi> As in all Iewish and Christian salutation,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119987:20"/> ministeriall, and Apostolicall benediction; Is any Prayer in Scripture more plaine <hi>then mercy and Peace be with you? The Peace of GOD rule your hearts and minds,</hi> and the like. Thirdly, The <hi>purchase and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement of Peace</hi> directed to be by all condescension imaginable: As by offering peace, forbearing wrath, forgiving wrong, receding from some thing of Right, and undergoing much of sorrow and affliction; Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of a Mediator, earnest intreaty and expostu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and indeed what not: If wee will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to Iesus Christ, who hath not only condescen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Ambassadors of Peace to intreat Rebels, and enemies to be reconciled; but also left his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, became liable to his Fathers fury, humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to the death of the Crosse, and underwent the Chastisement of our Peace; That <hi>whilest wee were yet enemies, GOD he might be reconciled unto us:</hi> Can I say these things be considered by a sensible Soule, and it not stand convinced that the enjoyment of peace is indispensably necessary? nay, can any man consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Outcries of meere men after peace with a <hi>Pax bello potior,</hi> Peace before War? Yea, <hi>pacem ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quissimam justissimo bello antefero,</hi> the worst peace ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the best warre;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Oh hanc ipsam causam bella suscipienda ut in pace sine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juria vivatur. <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>pacem te poscimus Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> all men even the martiall Medes, and warlike Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians themselves desire Peace; and not determine surely peace is the one thing necessary for man? so necessary is the enjoyment of peace, that it and it only is <hi>the End, and so the Ground of lawfull Warre;</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nature nor Scripture will allow war to be waged so long as Peace can possibly be possessed: The ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of peace is exceeding great, for that without it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119987:20"/> wee cannot possesse our own enjoyments, preserve our Laws or liberties, or participate of the endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments each of other: Times of War, strife, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention are times of Rapine, violence and discontent; tumult and commotion of mans outward, and inward estate, wherein his Title to the best possession is of little value; the clearest Right will not secure from military Spoile, and violence; <hi>Inter arma silent Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> Souldiers know no right <hi>but Plunder,</hi> nor Law <hi>but Power,</hi> War hindreth the Husbandmans labour, the Marchants Trade, the Sea-mans Navigation, and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t zens order; and in a Moment strips naked of all enjoyments, runs into all confusion and commotion: That which is left to us is so embittered by Alarums, and affrighting feares of the approaching Fire and Sword; That it cannot be enjoyed with any content or satisfaction, none but Fooles will seeke to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves great things in a land of War, and contention; for <hi>poverty is the usuall product of Warre,</hi> all order, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Interest cease in dayes, and places of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion: For indeed peace can only preserve them and propagate them: It is of peace that the Poets doe sing, —
<q>
                  <l>Pace Dei Cultus, Legum{que} verenda potestas;</l>
                  <l>et sacra musarum gloria, pace v<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>get:</l>
                  <l>Pace suas M<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rcator opes, sua Rura colonus</l>
                  <l>p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssidet; absque metu carpit &amp; h<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>spes iter.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>By Peace Gods Worship, mens Laws,<note place="margin">Sabin.</note> the Muses pleasures, Marchants Treasure, Husbandmans labour, Sojourners safety, and all other enjoyments are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served: Therefore peace is accounted <hi>all Perfection,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:119987:21"/> and as wee before noted it implies all kind of Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings whatsoever: Peace is the <hi>Spring of participati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> all Communion is founded in Union; The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies of nature, endowments and acquirements of Art, are not communicated among men, but by peace: <hi>The excellencies of Nature</hi> distributed into the severall Nations of the earth, are by War bolted out from the enjoyment each of other; but Peace is the Turn-key which opens the passage of all commerce and Trade, the <hi>Endowments of mind</hi> disposed by God for the mutuall Good each of other, are obstructed by strife and contention, and only communicated by U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Amity: And therefore the Apostle doth exceedingly wel advise <hi>to follow the things of peace, and edifie one another,</hi> Rom. 14.19. Discord among men saith TERTVLLIAN doth <hi>edificare in Gehennam,</hi> build backward; for by strife men do hide Counsell each from other: much might be spoken to amplifie the necessity of Peace, but time calls mee to hasten; Let it therefore suffice, that if wee would sit under our Vines, and eat the Fruit of our own Figge-trees, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low our Trades and Callings with content; be secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as to Law, Liberty, or Religion, or participate of the good things by GOD and Nature entrusted with other Nations or Persons: Wee must see peace indispensably necessary to be enjoyed; and therefore to be sought and pursued: So much then for the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of the Object.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pursuit of peace necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note>The <hi>Object</hi> is not more necessary to be enjoyed then the <hi>Act of seeking and pursuing:</hi> Peace is necessary to be sought and pursued, for indeed the necessity of the one must constraine the other; and that the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119987:21"/> because it is not obvious to every eye, nor ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily obtained; it is not to be had at any time, and on any Termes a Man may goe as <hi>farre as is possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and in him lyeth</hi> in pursuit of Peace, and yet miss of it; for he may meet with <hi>unreasonable men,</hi> for <hi>all men have not Faith:</hi> But I would enlarge the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity of the duty of seeking Peace and pursuing it by these three or foure Christian considerations.</p>
            <p>First, <hi>Jt is a commanded Duty:</hi> Nature hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed it on all mens minds, and Scripture doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyne it on all that are called the Children of God; ISRAEL commissioned to cut his way to <hi>Canaan,</hi> is commanded to <hi>seeke Peace at</hi> every place, and <hi>pursue it at</hi> all Cities, before they breake into and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime War, <hi>Deut.</hi> 20. And our Tutors lesson to his Children is in the Text, <hi>Seeke Peace and pursue it;</hi> and the great Command of the Gospell is <hi>to bee at peace among our selves,</hi> 1. Thes. 5.13, <hi>as farre as it is possible what in you lyeth live peaceably with all Men,</hi> Rom. 12.18; He must shut his eyes that will looke into Gods word, and not run and reade this Lesson: And hee must then stubbornly disobey the Gospell, that is not convinced of a necessity to seeke Peace and pursue it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This is the <hi>Course of life to which Chris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians are called:</hi> The Engagement of domestique concord, and discharge of the relative duty of a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever to an Infidell is; that <hi>GOD hath called us unto Peace,</hi> 1. Cor. 7.15. and in this respect Peace is said to be the <hi>formality of the Kingdome of God,</hi> or estate of Grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17; the <hi>essentiall property of the Wisdome from above</hi> is to be peaceable, gentle and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119987:22"/> to be intreated, <hi>Iames,</hi> 43.17. the very <hi>Genius and disposition</hi> of the Regenerated is Man united unto Christ, and animated by the Spirit; <hi>To be spiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minded is Peace,</hi> Rom. 8.6. so that such as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare the Children of Peace, and answer the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to which they are called must seeke Peace and pursue it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>It conformeth unto God:</hi> Christians ought to walke as IESVS CHRIST hath walked,<note place="margin">Ephes. 4.1.</note> and as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving GOD for our Example, and that is in Love and Long suffering, and labouring after Peace; It is the honourable Epithite and Title of God, that he is <hi>the God of Peace,</hi> and the happinesse of man that he is <hi>a God seeking Peace:</hi> Whilest we have rebelled against and run away from God, wee had been ruined, if hee had not sought our peace and pursued it; but he was so willing to be reconciled, that he <hi>looked for an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor, and wondered that there was none; then did his own right hand bring forth Salvation,</hi> Isa. 59.17: God was in CHRIST <hi>reconciling the World unto himselfe,</hi> 2. Cor. 5.19. out of his piety, and peaceable disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he provided for us <hi>a Propitiation,</hi> on whom hee laid the <hi>Chastisement of our peace;</hi> and whilest wee were yet enemies <hi>reconciled us unto himselfe,</hi> and hath committed to us the word of Reconciliation: In a word he createth and commandeth Peace to the ends of the Earth, and therefore such as will study to bee like God must seeke Peace and pursue it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It is the <hi>Companion of, and Comment on ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse:</hi> These two the Apostle joyneth together, as the best Ornament in accesse to God, like the Bels and Pomegranates on ARONS Garments in entring into
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119987:22"/> the Holy place; <hi>Follow peace and holinesse, without which no Man can see GOD,</hi> Heb. 12.14? and our Psalmist and Tutor maketh it one of the Lessons to be learned in the way of the feare of the Lord, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins with an <hi>I will teach you the feare of the Lord,</hi> and so proceedeth to a <hi>seeke peace and pursue it:</hi> nor doth the Apostle PETER in the Recitall and review of this instruction any way correct or invert the Order or Method propounded; But enforce and prescribe it 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11, by seeking and pursuing peace wee must speake our selves sanctified.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, It is <hi>the Conduct to life, true good, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine acceptance:</hi> As in the Text, and that of P<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>TER before cited, if <hi>any Man love Life, and would see good Dayes, he</hi> must seeke peace and pursue it answerable hereunto, is the appointment of the Apostle that <hi>men pray lifting up hands without Wrath,</hi> 1. Tim. 2.8; and that of our Saviours in <hi>Math.</hi> 5.23, 24, if <hi>thou bringest thy gift to the Altar, and there remembrest thy Brother hath ought against thee, leave there thy gift and goe, first be reconciled to thy Brother, then come and offer thy gift?</hi> Prayer presented from a wrathfull brest cannot prevaile with the God of peace: If wee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give not men their Trespasses, God will not forgive ours, and therefore there is a necessity of seeking Peace and pursuing.</p>
            <p>I have done with the Reasons of the Doctrine, and laid before you <hi>Excellency</hi> to engage ingenuity; and <hi>indispensable necessity</hi> of Peace, and the pursuit of it <hi>to enforce</hi> the backward and more rude, that if wee wish well to our selves, will obey the command of God, and call of the Gospell; if wee will conforme
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119987:23"/> to God, and commend our own piety, or come with confidence into Gods presence by Prayer for bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings: Wee may be constrained to seeke Peace and pursue it, I shall now passe to the Application; which will bee double by way of reproofe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vse of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe.</note>The first use I shall make of this Doctrine is, <hi>By way of Reproofe;</hi> seeing good mens care should be to seeke peace and pursue it: They are justly liable to blame who <hi>stand estranged unto Peace, and drive it at a distance from themselves and others:</hi> who make Strife their only study, and contest for nothing more then to maintaine contention; Salamanders that can live no where but in the Fire, tumultuous persons who love to fish in troubled waters; and therefore slight Peace when ever it is propounded; but by all possible meanes foment and further strife and debate, and that as well to themselves, as among others; <hi>they bare peace,</hi> and when men seeke peace and speake thereof they are <hi>wholy bent for Warre,</hi> like PHILLIP of <hi>Macedon,</hi> who to keepe up the Heart and Courage of his Souldiers usually said <hi>to us, Peace is Warre and Warre is peace:</hi> In their pride they are ever provoking, and in envy encouraging unto debate, and contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and by their wrathfull Spirits stirring up strife, snuffing at all condescensions, and scorning all things which tend to Composure, and many times by Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shood and flattery make Debate amongst Others: However they may sometimes speake of Peace, their words be smooth as Butter, yet <hi>Warre is in their Hearts;</hi> Wicked men like the troubled Sea they <hi>never rest,</hi> but are actively as well as passively tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119987:23"/> alwaies <hi>casting out Mire and Clay:</hi> Whatever be their faire pretences, a serious view of their carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age doth give us cause to conclude <hi>the Way of Peace they have not knowne,</hi> nor indeed doe they enquire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or desire to find it: As is evident by their peace declining, wrath provoking, strife fomenting practise in these particulers.</p>
            <p>First,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Evidence of slighted peace.</note>
               <hi>Prophanesse of Conversation</hi> provoking di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Iustice against themselves, and all such as any way stand related to them: GOD is a God of Iea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lousie, and cannot but punish iniquity, and being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked he puts a Period to the peace of the wicked; when he by his Prophets sounds an Alarum to ISRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>EL with an <hi>I have taken away my peace from this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> he doth declare the cause and reason to be this, <hi>yee have done worse then your Fathers, for behold every man walketh after the imagination of his own heart,</hi> Iere. 16.5.12. For men to fight against Gods holinesse and power by their prophanesse, and yet fancy to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves <hi>peace,</hi> it is a <hi>Wrath kindling security</hi> and <hi>provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king presumption; If any man heare the words of this curse, and blesse himselfe in his heart, and say, I shall have peace although I walke in the imagination of mine heart, and adde Drunkenesse to Thirst, the Lord will not spare him, but the wrath of the Lord and his Iealousie will smoake against that Man,</hi> Deut. 29.19.20: If the Kings of ISRAEL give themselves to worke wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, they must not thinke to settle their Thrones in peace, prophane men enquiring for peace must and will meet with JEHV's Answer to IORAM's demand, <hi>is it Peace</hi> IEHV? <hi>what peace so long us the Whoredoms of thy Mother</hi> IEZABELL <hi>and her witchcrafts are so
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119987:24"/> many,</hi> 2 Kings 9.22. In vaine doe wicked men by Pride and Perjury, Rioting and Drunkenness, Atheism and irreligion, wage warre with GOD, and pretend peace with Men; they that pursue Peace by provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Gods anger pursue it to expulsion not obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Evidence of slighted peace.</note>Secondly, <hi>Perversly invading other mens interests;</hi> Force must bee removed by force, Content with a mans owne love is that which maketh and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth concord; the unjust extension of Dominion, by breaking bonds, and usurpation of other mens powers, and invasion of their interests, are on all hands acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be the inchoation of strife and inlet of war, into the world; the Iron age which exild justice, and content; and filled mens minds with a greedy appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite of gaine and glory; is acknowledged to be the Age of discord and confusion: when no mans enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments could be secured, but all had cause to complain <hi>Vivitur ex rapto non hospes ab hospite tutus,</hi> All men lived by Rapine and violence, no man was secure by another; God threatens warre and spoyling to the Spoyler, <hi>Isa.</hi> 33.1. Nature doth not more animate then Scripture allow that men should <hi>Vim vi repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere,</hi> resist and withstand violence; in vaine doth A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HAB think in peace to enjoy the pleasure of NABOTHS Vineyard, when he hath no better tenure then that he <hi>hath killed and taken Possession,</hi> and no other title but violence and Perjury: <hi>Lust and desire to have</hi> may lead to strife and violence and easily engender warre; but though men acted by it <hi>doe kill, fight and warre,</hi> and use all unjust meanes, they have not nor can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a Peaceable possession of their unjust desires,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119987:24"/>
               <hi>Iames,</hi> 4.1, 2. For though an impotencie in the party invaded, and injured, may promise them security; yet <hi>for the sighing of the needy and cry of the oppressed, God will arise to set him in safety,</hi> in Psal. 12.5. The hire of the Labourer which is kept by force and fraud, and the cryes of them that reape the fields of proud Oppressors, doth cry in the eares to the great distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of the Lord of Rest or Saboth, (<hi>Iames</hi> 5.5.) nor must men thinke by Prayer, Fasting and formalities of Religion, to palliate their violence, injustice, and oppression; for whilest they fast for strife and debate and so smite with fist of wickedness, their voyce can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be heard on high nor will God accept them, <hi>Isa.</hi> 58.34. To devour Widowes houses, and for pretence to make long prayers doth but expose men to a woe and greater condemnation, <hi>Math.</hi> 23.14. Such there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as by Rapine and violence, invade other mens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terests; and by usurpation exercise other mens pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and enjoy their Proprieties; are never contented with their owne possessions, but lust after and by right or wrong obtaine or detaine what belongs to others, doe not only slight Peace, but pursue it, as an enemy to expell it their Coasts &amp; borders, least it set bounds to their Covetousnesse and ambition, and restraine their injustice, violence and oppression.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proud selfe advancement:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Evidence of slighted Peace.</note> Pride is owned by all men as the <hi>Ruine</hi> of vertue, and Root of all vice, the first in all sin, and last in all strife; And the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects thereof must needs be arraigned as the slighters of Peace, for Pride and the Pursuit of peace are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consistent, SOLOMON hath resolved <hi>that only from pride commeth Contention,</hi> Prov. 13.10. And shall we but se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119987:25"/> consult the strifes of Families, seditions of Republiques, and schismes in the Church, they will all soone appeare to have sprang from Pride; This is that <hi>diabolicall disposition</hi> that put the Angels into an opposition of their Creator, this is <hi>the Grand make bate</hi> among men of all Rankes and Orders, that high form of Spirit which admits no Peeres, much lesse Superiours; its only language is <hi>aut Caesar aut nullus,</hi> either the highest or no body: This is that <hi>boundlesse property</hi> that cannot endure to be prescribed by Law, or confined by any Bankes, but to advance its own inventions, will contend with men and as much as may be with the Majesty of Heaven; to this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour nothing but singularity and superiority can give content, this is the <hi>Mother of envy,</hi> injustice, oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and cruelty those grand Barres to peace: <hi>By pride</hi> Men grudge the Prosperity and Preheminence of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and pricke up into a claime of parity, where God himselfe hath made the difference, all ISRAEL must be led into Commotion and Disturbance, one while by the Pride of AARON and MIRIAM, envying MOSES honour with an <hi>hath the Lord spoken by</hi> MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SES <hi>only, and hath he not spoken by us also,</hi> Numb. 12.2? and another while made to mutiny, against all or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and authority with a proud out-cry, <hi>all the Lords people are holy, ye</hi> MOSES <hi>and</hi> AARON <hi>take too much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you,</hi> Numb. 19.3; <hi>Pride</hi> ever beholds other mens honours and <hi>enjoyments</hi> by the multiplying glasse of Envy, and so it stirreth up emulation, strife, hatred, enmity, and Contention: From hence hath sprung all those perfidies, Warres, Commotions, Rebellions, perjuries, usurpations, and treasonable bloudy invasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119987:25"/> whereby Kingdomes have been racked and rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: <hi>Pride</hi> doth not more envy the enjoyments, then <hi>exercises and endowments</hi> of others; all men affecting Excellency cannot but contend for Mastery, whilest things are done by vaine glory, they must bee done in strife, the Crown of pride cannot be fastened other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise then by the Calumny of all that exceed or equall the atchievements of proud men: ELIAB cannot but <hi>in Pride</hi> charge <hi>Pride</hi> on his Brother DAVID, but for enquiring after the Atchievement, himselfe or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Host of ISRAELL durst not undertake, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 28. nay, <hi>Pride</hi> cannot but contemne the very Essayes, and undertakings of men in their eyes une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to themselves; DAVIDS onset on GOLIAH was not more contemptible in the eyes of that proud Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, then in the eyes of SAVL and the whole host of <hi>Israell;</hi> Excellency shining with unexpected splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, doth enrage proud persons to the height of enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and study of destruction of the more worthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, what was the ground of SAVL's hatred and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting after DAVID, save that the women in <hi>Israell</hi> had advanced DAVIDS praise, SAVL <hi>hath slaine his Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand, but</hi> DAVID <hi>his ten Thousands,</hi> 1. Sam. 18.8. where Pride cannot destroy the more worthy person, it will apt a man to destroy himselfe, proud AHITOPHELL will hang himselfe, if but outwitted by HVSHAI his Counsell; such is the unreasonablenesse of this wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed passion and proud humour, that it will on meere toyes, trifles and punctilioes of no moment, involve men into the most intollerable broyles and deadly fewds imaginable: the very want of a beck of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, a cap or knee of honour, and that of one MOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DECAI
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119987:26"/> will excite the wrath of a proud HAMAN, to the extirpation of all <hi>Israell,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.21. <hi>Pride</hi> is picking quarrels on all occasions, and provoking en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and strife on slender causes; nor will it hearken to the least of reason for reconciliation; it scornfully rejects all perswasions unto Peace, and casts off all convictions of evils that arise in themselves; IONA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THAN's intreaties are of no force to allay the rage of SAVL; nor will the convictions of DAVID's inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity confest by himselfe checke this proud passion. <hi>Pride</hi> cannot endure the least of contradiction; if CLITVS dare but check ALEXANDER's boasting by reckoning up the Victories obtained by his owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it may cost him his life. This is that <hi>Churlish disposition</hi> which may expose NABALS house to Ruine, by the proud deniall of a common kindness: This is that <hi>tyrannicall Spirit</hi> that can receive no submission, heare no intreaties, and be satisfied in nothing but tryumphs of cruelty, though it self becomes the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of greater pitty, then is requested from it: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by men proudly exact the utmost mite and show not the least of Patience to a fellow servant indebted but <hi>an hundred pence,</hi> though themselves procure the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of <hi>Ten thousand talents,</hi> Math. 18.22, 23, 24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that this being the knowne nature of Pride, such as pamper and please themselves in it must so farre provoke God and man, and prove turbulent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet, that they cannot possesse Peace, nor indeed care to seeke or pursue it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Evidence of slighted Peace.</note>But a fourth sort to be blamed as shunning Peace and indeed staving it off, from themselves or others, are <hi>Prating busie bodyes, make-bates</hi> that are alwayes
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119987:26"/> medling in other mens matters: These are in nature the very Pest of the people, and professed obstruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Peace; SALOMON doth oppose the <hi>Fooles medling</hi> unto <hi>a ceasing from strife,</hi> Prov. 20.3. Of this sort are all <hi>Tale-bearers</hi> who goe up and downe with reports in which themselves are not concerned, nor can they produce any other end, save strife and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, wrath and enmity; these are SOLOMONS <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men,</hi> who doe indeed <hi>dig up strife,</hi> their lips are as <hi>a burning fire,</hi> by their whispering they seperate the dearest friends, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.27. for <hi>as Wood is to the fire, and Coales to burning Coales, so are these contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men,</hi> Prov. 20.21: These Men by foolish Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and false accusations stirre up envy implaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, cursed Doegs that excite the Cruelty of SAVL to cut off the very Priests of God; and shamelesse Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bahs by their suggestions stirring up a most just DA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VID to an enmity against an innocent MEPHIBO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHETH, these men doe wound others, and engage them to continuall Warres, and many times take themselves a Dog by the eare, which they can neither hold, nor let goe without hurt: DAVID hath read the doome of these grand disturbers of Peace in Psal. 120.3, 4. <hi>What shall be given unto thee? or what shall be done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, thou false tongue? sharp Arrowes of the Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with coales of Iuniper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the last fort whom I shall charge with a sligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Peace, avoiding it in themselves,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Evidence of slighted peace.</note> obstructing other mens enjoyment of it are <hi>prejuicate minds and suspicious heads,</hi> who are subject to surmises, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all jealousies, and groundlesse feares; conceiving all designes to be laid, and all words to be spoken against
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119987:27"/> themselves: confiding in no assurances that can bee given, and therefore consent not to any accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions can be offered, suspicion is ever quick witted, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the least and unlikely occasion makes such mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubt, the event of which they are afraid, feare affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it selfe with bugs of terror, which stand up against Peace; all pleas are in vaine, and perswasions boot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse to them, who are deafned with their own feare, a fearefull man can never be a fast or faithfull friend, this trembling passion will neither trust, nor keepe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny termes of peace: but waite for (what they thinke others watch) an opportunity of violence, and despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate escape from surmised danger: feare frequently flowing from guilt is that which makes men <hi>fly when none pursueth,</hi> faithlesse in what they promise; fierce and cruell to all that fall in their Power, according to the Greeke proverb, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>timidus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micida est,</hi> he that feares is ready to slay and kill: This is as the Orator observes the ordinary state of a<note n="*" place="margin">Haec est vita Tyrannorum in quae nulla est fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des; nulla cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas, nulla sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis bene volen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae fiducia, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia semper su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specta atque sollicita nullus locus est amici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, In <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </note> Tyrant in whom there can be no faith, no stable assurance of good will, no ground of Amity, because he holds all things in suspicion, and soul tormenting care and Surmises; Power gotten by Usurpation is held with suspicion, and ordinarily lost with shame: Subjects of Rebellion are distractfully doubtfull of their Soveraignes pardon, and therefore study to barre peace from amongst them, rather then returne to their allegiance, how many Out-cries for Acts of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity are uttered by the disturbers of Peace; and yet their suspicious head never satisfied, stirre up new broiles, and commotions with a pretence of Necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the securing of themselves: They run dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119987:27"/> and desperate Hazards who feare revenge, and measuring all mens minds by their own feares, fancy, or necessity of perpetuall enmity; and impobssility of agreement and reconciliation: but I must not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large.</p>
            <p>Wee see then who they are that stave off Peace, when it approacheth, so farre are they from <hi>seeking or pursuing it,</hi> that they fly from it, and expell it, and herein their sin is exceeding sinfull in that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the dictate of Nature, directions of Scripture, degenerate from the property of good men, degrade their own Spirits, and demonstrate themselves despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately wicked, and their sorrow is sufficiently heavy, when summed up into this short Compendium, <hi>as they loved not Peace, so it shall bee farre from them:</hi> And so much for the use of <hi>Reproofe,</hi> I must briefly passe over the second.</p>
            <p>The second use is of Exhortation to perswade with every of us in our severall places and capacities to <hi>seeke Peace, and to pursue it:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Vse to Exhort.</note> Let you and me labour to live in peace among our selves, and as farre as may be have peace with all men; let us seeke and pray for the Peace of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> the Church of God, and the Land of our Nativity, as ever wee will approve our selves good men, walking in the feare of the Lord, and waiting to see long life, and good dayes, <hi>let us fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after the things which make for Peace:</hi> I shall not need to spend time in urging motives, if wee have but hearts affected with the Excellency or Necessity of Peace, wee find Arguments of no lesse efficacy to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade the will, then force to convince the mind of this duty, give me leave to lay before you some few
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119987:28"/> directions unto those things which tend to Peace and I have done.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Helpe of Peace.</note>First, In the Pursuit of peace <hi>affect Truth:</hi> Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shood stirreth up fury, Error hath caused all those earnest contests which have filled the Church with commotion; mistaken minds do manage Debates with mutinies: Wee (my Brethren) have had sad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the evill of Error, and violence of Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Rage, and enmity, if God but open your eyes to see the errors withstood, you would not contend against Gods Ministers who must be as ATHANASIVS, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Pillers of Truth;</hi> receiving and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling all the shafts of false Doctrine, and Opinions have shot against the Faith, HEZEKIAHS content must be ours, <hi>it is good that Peace and Truth be in my dayes</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Zach 8.16.</note> Kings, 20.19. this may not be divided: It is a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Love to peace that leadeth into such moderation, as to loose our zeale for Truth, &amp; give God cause to complaine,<note place="margin">Ierem. 9.3.</note> that when the wicked <hi>bend their tongues like bowes</hi> for lies, his people are not <hi>valiant for the truth;</hi> assent to Truth, agreement in Doctrines of faith must be the ground of Amity: It is a <hi>Moderation</hi> not more hardly attained, then obscurely allowed in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, under divided judgements to imbrace with cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and hearty affections; Whilest therefore you seeke peace, see error, shun Seducers, <hi>know them that have made divisions among you contrary to the Doctrine you have received,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note>
               <hi>and avoid them?</hi> shake hands with, stand at a distance from false Teachers, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them not into your houses,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Iohn, 10.</note>
               <hi>bid them not GOD speed?</hi> much lesse thrust them with Violence into your Churches, and spend your time under their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119987:28"/> But be ready earnestly <hi>to contend for the faith which hath been delivered to the Saints,</hi> Iude, 3. and in Zeale to peace give me leave to wish with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle, <hi>they were even cut off who trouble you,</hi> Gal. 5.12. and let me prescribe this advise, as the first and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation act tending to be at peace in 1. Cor. 1.10, <hi>now I beseech you Brethren by the name of the Lord</hi> IESVS CHRIST, <hi>that ye all speake the same thing, and that there be no division among you, but that you be perfectly joyned together in the same mind, and in the same judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> For if you leave not the way of Error,<note place="margin">Iohn. 2.2.</note> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace not the Truth in the love of it, and love Men and Ministers for the Truth-sake which is in them, your Peace cannot be long.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In the Pursuit of peace <hi>attend Order:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Helpe to Peace.</note> march in Ranke and file, take head of mutinies, and confusions? Peace is the end of War, but Souldiers of disorder will never fight to effect it: Wee have before told you that peace in humane society is <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata tranquilitas,</hi> as AVSTIN doth define it, <hi>orderly se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renitie: Serenity</hi> doth not more formally constitute Peace, then <hi>Order</hi> doth constitute Serenity; for the same, AVSTIN directing a prudent Pursuit of our own peace of mind doth advise to the order of all present affaires, actions, enjoymenrs, and oppressions, rendring this Reason, <hi>Ordo mentem quietam reddit,</hi> Order qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets the mind: The course of mans life is calme and smooth, when he knoweth how to take and leave, when to moove and stand still, the series of Providence in the disposition of all created beings is not more the honour, then satisfaction of God; as ever wee will have Peace let us <hi>attend Order,</hi> keepe our places, wait
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119987:29"/> on God in our stations, serve God in our Callings and Capacity, keepe that order God hath appointed among men, Superiours must be observed by inferiors, and equals carry orderly one towards another: the inversion of Order is the in let of all Commotion, strife and War, the Soveraignty of servants puts the whole Earth into a shaking fit, that it cannot sustaine in selfe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.21, 22, in Families, Church, or Kingdome, Confusion cannot but produce commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and therefore the Apostolicall Rule in order to the Churches peace is, <hi>let all things be done decently and in order,</hi> 1. Cor. 14.40. and the Argument to enforce it is, <hi>GOD is not the God of Confusion</hi> (or as the Greeke tumultuation) <hi>but of Peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1 Cor. 14.33.</note> where by the way note that disorder is a formall <hi>Tumultuation,</hi> and so is opposed to peace: And the Apostle directing unto Peace, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth unto Order with a <hi>Know them that are over you in the Lord, and be at peace among your selves,</hi> 1. Thes. 5.12, 13. Unruly Servants, and disorderly Children must be chastised; Rebels reduced, and perverse in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusions rebuked and restrained, and so peace is barred, when the foot aspireth to be the Head, and the hand the Eye, the Body must needs be discomposed: Christians! as you desire Peace know your places, and abide in them, keepe order, and so shall you pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesse Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Helpe to Peace.</note>Thirdly, In the pursuit of Peace <hi>act justly:</hi> Bee content with your own things, invade not other mens interests, offer violence to no man, <hi>Oppression will make a wise man mad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccles. 7.7.</note> and madnesse will easily make mutinies, and Commotion; wee ordinarily say of a worme <hi>tread on it it will turne againe,</hi> and it is an act
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119987:29"/> allowed by all <hi>Ʋim vi repellere,</hi> Nature hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished the Beast with hornes, the Fish with finnes, the Bee with a sting to be put forth when provoked to their owne defence; shall Men thinke to tread on mens Proprieties, and yet triumph in Peace by foolish clamours, and false accusations, extrajudiciall processe, and positive Perjury, you will persecute a man in his Name, Estate, and being, and yet thinke to enjoy Peace, Nature will not admit it, nor doth Scripture enjoyne it: You have heard how Injustice doth stave off Peace, I have no pleasure to harp on this harsh string, nor rippe up Wounds when healed, I will say no more, save intreat you to shun Oppression, and let Righteousnesse and Peace imbrace each other, execute the judgement of Truth, and Peace in your Gates, <hi>Zacharias,</hi> 8.16.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Helpe to Peace.</note> In the Pursuit of peace <hi>Abide hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:</hi> I have before noted how through Pride <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth</hi> Contention, and enlarged on the naturall ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of that sinne unto all Strife and commotion, my advise to you is that of the Apostles, <hi>Let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing bee done through strife and vaine glory, but in lowlinesse of mind, each esteeme others better then themselves,</hi> Phil. 2.3. Take heed of Pride; for the swellings of it will make you <hi>sawcy</hi> towards Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, <hi>surly</hi> with Equals, and <hi>over-sterne</hi> with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours; so that you will be picking quarrels on weake grounds, on all occasions, and no small mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will satisfie your expectations, nor qualifie your passions, Pride will provoke you to Injustice, Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and Envy, that you shall doe no right, nor
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119987:30"/> take no wrong, and then it is not likely you should live in peace: The wisdome which is from above, and so peaceable, is first Meeke, gentle, and easie to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Helpe to Peace.</note>Fifthly, In the Pursuit of peace <hi>avoid Offences, acknowledge them when Committed, and Forgive them when acknowledged:</hi> Offence begins the broile, and therefore <hi>keepe a Conscience void of offence towards GOD and Man;</hi> the peaceable Spirit of PAVL would <hi>give none offence to Iew or Greeke,</hi> (1. Cor. 10.32.) In <hi>Adiaphoraes</hi> or things indifferent; bee but willing to gratifie one another, so shall you live in Peace; for they that will not offend in the use of Liberty, will not dare to intrench on Duty by doing acts of Violence and Injustice: <hi>Offence</hi> doth not so soone begin, as <hi>Obstinacie</hi> heighten and provoke a Contest and opposition: Penuance is the poorest part that can bee imposed on the party of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending; and the same GOD that promiseth <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to men,</hi> doth require <hi>Confession from men;</hi> If wee <hi>confesse,</hi> hee is faithfull and ready to <hi>Forgive us our sinne,</hi> (1. Iohn, 1.9;) and the same CHRIST who doth enjoyne us to forgive an offending Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>till Seventy times seven,</hi> (Math. 18.22.) doth engage the Offendor as often <hi>to returne and say, I have offended:</hi> Obstinacy doth not more provoke then <hi>Obduracie</hi> doth perpetuate an enmity: an implacable Spirit is the very effect of Envie, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of strife: Submission and readinesse to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution, is all the Satisfaction for the offence committed, which can be desired, though wee may not sinne, that <hi>Grace may abound,</hi> when wee have
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119987:30"/> sinned <hi>Grace must abound;</hi> Repentance is (before GOD and Man) the spunge of guilt, God no sooner heareth DAVID cry, <hi>I have sinned,</hi> but hee answers, <hi>I have Forgiven thine offence,</hi> (2. Sam. 12.13.) And hee requires of Man, that as often as the Brother returneth and saith, <hi>I have offended,</hi> wee doe forgive him, though not untill then yet so soone the pardon of a past offence must be sealed, a rigorous exaction of Satisfaction, or exercise of Retaliation is but a little short of Revenge: It is base and belluine to trample on a dead Lion, or triumph over yeilding Enemies; <hi>true Nobility</hi> is alwaies stayed <hi>by the submission of an Enemy,</hi> whilest <hi>Cruelty to the conquered</hi> is base and belluine: Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently well doth the Poet set out this property;
<q>
                  <l>Quo quis{que} est major; magis est placabilis irae,</l>
                  <l>et faciles motus, mens generosa capit</l>
                  <l>Corpora magnanimo satis est prostrasse Leoni;</l>
                  <l>pugna suum finem, cum Jacet hostis habet:</l>
                  <l>At Lupus &amp; turpes instant morientibus Vrsi,</l>
                  <l>et quaecun{que} minor, Nobilitate fera est.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Noble Spirits that will not receive affronts will yet with ease restraine provoked wrath, and bee pacified by the entreaties of yeilding Enemies, though Wolfe and Beare may rend the dead body, the Lion will scorne to touch the Prostrate; like that noble Emperour, who abhorred the motion of Slaughter of his conquered Enemies; saying, <hi>I am satisfied in the Victory, I seeke not their bloud.</hi> They who regard not to <hi>Avoid offences;</hi> that <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge</hi> them not when committed, and <hi>Exact the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119987:31"/> utmost mite</hi> from a prostrate Offendor without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission in the least must never thinke to possesse Peace: If the Master on submission forgive <hi>Ten thousand Talents,</hi> the Servant may well remit <hi>an hundred Pence:</hi> Let us remember <hi>summum, jus</hi> is <hi>summa injuria,</hi> the rigour of Justice, runnes into wrong, Cruelty, and Injustice.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>6.</hi> Helpe of Peace.</note>The Sixth and last direction I shall give you in the Pursuit of peace is, <hi>That</hi> you <hi>abound in Love:</hi> Looke each on other as you are in Nature, or Christianity, without that distastfull demeanour which your Passions have put you upon: and hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward, let <hi>brotherly Love increase,</hi> and be carefull to walke in love; For Love is <hi>the life of all Grace,</hi> Meeknesse, Humility, Patience, Long sufferance, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinesse to Forgive, are all animated by Love and the fruits thereof: Love is the <hi>Line of all duty</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards GOD and Man, dictating unto Order, and all orderly discharge of Duty, and directing in all that Labyrinth of difficulties, which entangle the way of our Peace, and is therefore said to bee the fulfilling of the Law, (<hi>Gal.</hi> 5.14.) Love is the <hi>limit of Authority,</hi> and so the b<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>kes of Pride, whereby Power and places of Honour, and posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Treasures are bounded, that they breake not into Scorne, Contempt, and Cruelty: Love is the <hi>Loadstone of Peac<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> advancing Unity; alluring an assent to Principles, and agreement of minds; avoiding Offences, acquitting Wrongs, and abating Jealousies, those make bates among Men, abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Tale-bearers,</hi> and Slaunders, which blow up the very sparkes of Contention, and involve us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119987:31"/> all kind of variance; and therefore as ever you desire to live in Peace, <hi>Love one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus then I have given you the directions which lead to Peace, may you and I pray that the <hi>Peace of GOD may rule our hearts and minds,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force our Prayer by practising these Duties pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, <hi>(viz.)</hi> First, affecting Truth. 2. Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Order. 3. Acting justly. 4. Abiding Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. 5.ly, Avoyding Offences; acquitting Wrongs acknowledged, and acknowledging them that they may bee acquitted, and abounding in Love one towards another: So shall the <hi>Peace of GOD, which passeth all understanding keepe our hearts and minds blamelesse unto the Comming of our Lord</hi> IESVS CHRIST.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>Thou art desired with a little care to observe some small <hi>Errors</hi> in Letters and Pointing, which may obstruct the sence in reading; but with thy Pen correct these words which have escaped the Presse, and doe alter the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the sentence to which they Relate. <hi>viz.</hi> — In</p>
            <p>Page 5. line 28. <hi>beholdeth,</hi> read betrotheth, pa. 6 l. 19 <hi>impossibility, r.</hi> insen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibility, l. 23 <hi>as, r.</hi> or, pa. 8 l. 4. <hi>infested, r.</hi> interested, l. <hi>r.</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> pa. 10. l. 10. <hi>wind, r.</hi> mind p. 12. l. 31. <hi>r.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. in, p. 21 l. 3. <hi>r.</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 27. l. 23. <hi>vevace, r. venale,</hi> l. 27. <hi>alone, r.</hi> Shalom, p. 28. l. 6. <hi>r.</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p 34. l. 2. read not <hi>is,</hi> p 38. l 9 <hi>Love, r.</hi> let.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>